Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today we've
got some kids for you in this dialogue.
They're doing something that's
very common in America, I'm not
so sure if it's common elsewhere,
but we'll find that out later.
So today we're going to ask for money
because we are having a fund razor.
So this is a very
interesting word.
Why don't we take a look
at it in vocabulary preview?
Very vocabulary preview.
So fund razor is a thing.
It's an event. It's something
that you do at a school
or a business to try and collect money for
a special event or charity. That's right.
So money you can also say is
funds, right? And that's what
you're trying to do.
You're trying to collect.
You're trying to gather a
lot of money or funds in
order for like you say some
sort of objective purpose.
Right, but it's not
just like we're having
a fund razor to earn
more profits this year.
It's usually an event that's for
some kind of charity or good cause.
So for example, the
company is having a fund
razor for Jenny's child
because he's sick and they
can't pay for medical care. Right.
So fund razor is for a good cause. Exactly.
So that's what this
dialogue is all about today.
Why don't we listen to the dialogue for
the first time and we'll be back in a bit.
Okay, Mark. It's your time to
ring the doorbell. I did it last time.
I hate going door to door
and I hate asking for money.
But we need to raise
enough money for the school
fund razor so that our
class can win the pizza party.
You do want to have a pizza party,
don't you? Yes, but just go already.
No one's coming. Try again.
Maybe there's no one home.
Of course there's someone home.
There are two cars in the
driveway and I can see lights
on in the house.
Hello, anybody home?
We would like to know if
you want to sponsor us in our
school fund razor. 50% of the profits
go towards the new school playground.
I don't know why anyone
would want what's in
this catalog anyway.
It's just a bunch of tacky
Christmas ornaments.
Cities of old people singing
Christmas signs and
special crackers and cheeses
and boxes of chocolates.
You don't like chocolate?
Not this kind. They've
got weird names like
ganache and paralean. Look, I just
saw someone walking around inside.
These people are
being very rude.
Finally, someone's coming.
They don't look too happy.
Hi sir, would you like
to sponsor us or make
a donation to you? Well,
great are you kids in?
Great seven. Then for
goodness sake, don't you see
this sign? Can't you
read? No soliciting.
All right, so obviously
the kids are selling candy
and a lot of different things for their new
playground. That's the fundraiser, right?
So they use a lot of interesting
words and phrases there.
Why don't we take a
look at a couple of them
on language takeaway?
Well, the first word is
one that Marco, you've
already talked a little
bit about today. We talked
about fundraiser to raise.
Well, we do have the
verb here to raise enough
money. So raise is a
verb that means to collect
or gather or to get. That's
right. So you wouldn't
really say we are
collecting money or we are
gathering money. You say
we are raising money for the
victims of the earthquake
in Haiti. That's right.
So the reason we don't
say we are earning money
is because you're not
doing any work. Right.
Really, you're not going
to the job at nine o'clock
and leaving the job at
five o'clock. You're actually
asking people for
donations. Exactly.
So that's what you're doing.
You are raising money and now
moving on another way
that you can help people
maybe through a charity or donation is also
to sponsor to sponsor someone or something.
Okay. So people can sponsor events or people
and companies can also do this as well.
So to sponsor someone
is basically to give them
money in support of a
cause. Right. For example,
have you ever done one of
those five K runs or 10 K runs?
Did you have to
collect sponsors?
Basically to find people who would
help pay money for you to do this run.
I'm not personally, but I know people who
have who actually get companies interested
and maybe that person
for example is going to
run five kilometers
in this race in order to
raise money for victims
of some serious illness.
And so they get sponsors. They get
companies to donate money for this cause.
Right. You could have a
person or company sponsor you.
They could be your
sponsor by giving you
money that you can then use
for this charity or special cause.
That's right. But the difference between
a fundraiser and to sponsor something or
someone is that
sponsoring is not always for a
charity or for some sort
of nonprofit cause. Right.
We have many sponsors for
concerts or for sporting events.
That's right. So oftentimes when you see
athletes, they have their sponsors or their
sponsors logos written
all over their jerseys.
Right. The clothes that
they wear. So for example,
if you're watching
Formula One racing, you see
the Ferrari and the the bank peblums and
all these different things. That's right.
So those are different ways
of sponsoring events or people.
And now moving on,
we have a word that's well
not really related to
money and fundraisers.
But it's a very interesting
word and very common
when the kids mentioned
that they're selling
a bunch of tacky Christmas
ornaments tacky tacky tacky.
Okay. You're going
to hear this a lot.
And the interesting
thing about the word tacky
is that it means something
different to everyone.
So what I think is tacky
might be just normal
for Marco and what
Marco thinks is really tacky
might be something
that I actually like. Right.
And so tacky is basically
a bad thing. It means
something is not good
looking or not very fashionable.
It's like in bad taste. But as you say,
taste is something subjective. Right.
So maybe for example,
sometimes we say that when girls
wear too much makeup,
it's very tacky, bright red
lipstick and blue
eyeshadow. Exactly.
So a guy might say, oh, that's
so tacky. Whereas another
person might not
think it's tacky at all.
So this happens a lot.
And we use this word a
lot with decorations, for
example, for someone's
house, you may
describe it as tacky or a
restaurant or a bar. Right.
So for maybe sometimes
those Italian restaurants
that have the red and
white checkered table
claws and other pictures
of the Italians with the
mustaches, I might think
that's a little bit tacky. But
maybe you think it's cute.
Right. So something
that's tacky.
And as we say, people
use it all the time.
And it's not necessarily a
bad thing. You can just say,
oh, it's a little bit tacky.
Or I think this thing
is a little bit tacky.
Okay. And that's it. Right.
So let's sit. So let's
sit. Okay. And our final
word on language takeaway
towards the end of the
dialogue when the kids
were reading the sign,
the sign said no
soliciting. And they didn't
understand what that
means. What does it mean
when you have a sign
that says no soliciting?
Okay. So to solicit is
to try to sell something
or to offer a service.
So basically the
sign means please don't come
to my house and salmy stuff.
Okay. For example, we have door to door,
insurance salesman or makeup sales people.
And these people go to
your door and they try to
sell you their products.
And no soliciting means
don't come to my house.
I'm not going to answer
the door if you're
trying to sell something.
So to solicit is to try
and sell something. Okay.
But usually in person,
trying to make a sale
uninvited, right? Because
if you're a businessman
and you have a
meeting, a sales meeting,
you're not really soliciting
with that other person.
No, this is basically trying to
sell something to a stranger.
Exactly. Okay. Very good.
So a lot of interesting
words there. Why don't we
listen to the dialogue again? And
we'll be back shortly with Fluency Builder.
Okay, Mark, it's your turn to
ring the doorbell. I did it last time.
I hate going door to door
and I hate asking for money.
But we need to raise
enough money for the
school fundraiser so that our
class can win the pizza party.
You do want to have a
pizza party, don't you?
Yes, but just go already. No one's coming.
Try again. Maybe there's no one home.
Of course there's someone
home. There are two cars
in the driveway and I can
see lights on in the house.
Hello, anybody home?
We would like to know
if you want to sponsor
us in our school fundraiser.
50% of the profits go towards
the new school playground.
I don't know why
anyone would want what's
in this catalog anyway. It's just a
bunch of tacky Christmas ornaments,
CDs of old people singing
Christmas songs and
special crackers and cheeses
and boxes of chocolates.
You don't like chocolate? Not this kind.
They've got weird names like
ganache and praline. Look, I just
saw someone walking around inside.
These people are
being very rude.
Finally, someone's coming.
They don't look too happy.
Hi, sir. Would you
like to sponsor us or
make a donation to?
What grade are you kids in?
Grade seven. Then for
goodness sake, don't you see
this sign? Can't you
read no soliciting?
All right, so now we're back
and we have four key phrases
for you on fluency
builder. Fluency builder.
Okay, this first phrase
is a pretty common one.
We wanted to make sure
that everyone was comfortable
with the verb that goes
with doorbell, so Marco,
what do you do to a
doorbell? You ring the doorbell.
You ring the doorbell.
So you don't touch it,
you don't press it, you can
press it, but you ring the doorbell.
That's the verb. Okay, so for example, when
I was a little, my brother and I always
used to fight about who
could ring the doorbell?
Really? Yes. I loved ring in
the doorbell and said it here.
Do you do the long ring or do you do the
ding, ding, ding, ding, ding, ding, ding.
The annoying ring. Yeah,
so to ring the doorbell.
All right, all right, and while going back,
when we were talking about no soliciting,
you said that salespeople
go door to door selling things.
So this is an interesting phrase, and
it's a fixed phrase going door to door.
Well, think about it. So
a salesperson who wants
to sell maybe some makeup
goes to one house and
no one wants to buy
any makeup there.
So she goes to the next house.
So she's going from house to
house, but we don't
really say house to house,
because she's going to your
door to offer the makeup.
So we just say
going door to door.
That means going to strangers
homes in order one door
after the next to sell
something. Very good.
You go door to door. So
you, for example, someone
can go door to door
asking for some sugar.
That's right. Or we could say
he is a door to door salesman.
Door to door
salesman. Very good.
All right. And now
we have an interesting
question, and it's a very
good one, because it's a
question that comes up a
lot. When somebody asks
you if you're studying, for
example, what grade are you in?
Okay, what grade are you in?
So in the American system,
for example, we have the very,
very bottom grade K,
which is kindergarten, for
maybe a five year old.
And at the very top, we have
high school grade 12.
Right. And so in between, we
have one, two, three,
four, five, you know, and up.
And so basically to
find out what year in
school, a student is, you
have to ask him or her,
what grade are you in?
Right. So then the person
would say, I'm in sixth
grade, I'm in eighth grade.
But this is the way you
ask this question for
a school, as you said,
a kid that's maybe five
years old, all the way to
18 years old in high school.
What grade are you
in? Now, if you're in
university and you want
to ask your friend, what
year of university that
person's in, then you say,
what year are you?
What year are you?
Yeah, you don't say grade.
So basically grade refers to,
like what you said, Marko,
those first 12 years of school.
And so we call them, we thought, no,
I don't call it grade. So you could ask
anybody under the age of
18, what grade are you in?
But when you go to
university or when you're
talking about university
students, it gets a little bit different.
So you can say, what year are you in or
what year are you? So if you're not sure
about someone's age and
you maybe think they're
in college, you can ask
them, what year are you?
But generally, anyone
under 18, what grade are you
in? Okay, good. All
right. And our last phrase,
and this is this kind
of an expression, right?
Goodness sake, for
goodness sake. Okay, so let's
look at the context,
the kids say, we're in
grade seven, and the
person at the door says,
then for goodness sake,
don't you see this sign?
Right, for goodness sake.
So this is an expression
that's used to indicate, maybe
you're a little bit frustrated.
Yes, right. So it's like, come on, or
my goodness, or for pizza sake, we
have many ways of
saying, all right, come on,
I'm a little tired of this.
Right, you're irritating
me. Right. So basically
the person saying,
you're too old for this,
you're too old for this.
You should read what it
says on my door, no soliciting.
Right. And so the
person's angry.
Right. The person's angry
because these kids are
trying to sell her
something. When clearly she
has a sign that says,
no soliciting. That's right.
Okay, a lot of
interesting phrases there.
Why don't we go back,
listen to our dialogue for
the very last time, and we'll be
back to talk with you a little bit more.
Okay, Mark, it's your time to
ring the doorbell. I did it last time.
I hate going door to door,
and I hate asking for money.
But we need to raise
enough money for the school
fundraiser so that our
class can win the pizza party.
You do want to have a pizza party,
don't you? Yes, but just go already.
No one's coming. Try again.
Maybe there's no one home.
Of course there's someone
home. There are two cars
in the driveway and I can
see lights on in the house.
Hello, anybody home?
We would like to know if
you want to sponsor us
in our school fundraiser.
50% of the profits go towards
the new school playground.
I don't know why anyone
would want what's in
this catalog anyway.
It's just a bunch of tacky
Christmas ornaments.
Cities of old people singing
Christmas signs and
special crackers and cheeses
and boxes of chocolates.
You don't like chocolate?
Not this kind. Got
weird names like
ganache and praline. Look, I just
saw someone walking around inside.
These people are
being very rude.
Finally, someone's coming.
They don't look too happy.
Hi, sir. Would you like to sponsor us
or make a donation to you? Well, great.
Are you kids in? Great
seven. Then for goodness sake,
don't you see this sign?
Can't you read? No soliciting.
All right, so door
to door salesman.
I think this used to be
a very American thing.
I think back in the 50s, you
would always see movies where
this was actually a
profession. That's right.
People would go door to
door selling hairbrushes or
magazines, subscriptions,
pretty much everything.
Yeah, you still
see it sometimes.
Some people sell insurance
or there are a lot of religious
door to door sales
people who want to sell
religious books or
magazines. But I think it was
much more popular in the
1950s because people didn't
really use their phones
as much to sell things.
It was cheaper to have
someone drive his car to
your neighborhood and
then go to every single house.
Right, right. But yeah,
it's a very interesting,
interesting job. I think
it would be very lonely.
And also, I think, well,
now maybe that's been
reduced to that because
now you have the internet.
Oh, yeah, well, the
internet means that the
salespeople come to you
without you having to get up.
Right. So basically, you're
sitting at home in your
pajamas and you can
order a TV and some clothes.
But it's very interesting
because I remember
you would have all these
door-to-door salesmen.
For example, I had one visit me
once who was selling me encyclopedias.
Really? A big collection
of like, I don't know,
37 books or more. It was a huge
amount of books encyclopedias.
And I don't know if
you see that anymore.
Not really. I don't
know if anyone buys
physical, huge encyclopedias to have in
their home. Now only collectors perhaps.
Maybe. Yeah. So it's a
very interesting profession.
I don't know. In the
United States, as you say,
it's not very common
anymore, very little, maybe
specific services.
But this is interesting,
maybe in your country,
this is still a big thing.
Yeah. Let us know in your
country, our door-to-door
salespeople still common.
Do you see them?
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
All right. Bye-bye. Bye.